JACOB Z. ELIASON

801 15th St S, Apt 1216, Arlington, VA | +1-801-473-3549 jacobeliason@gmail.com github.com/jcblsn | linkedin.com/in/jacobzeliason | jacobeliason.com US Govt Clearance Level: Secret Open to: in-person, hybrid, and remote positions Percent willing to travel: 50

SUMMARY

I am a data scientist and Master's candidate at the London School of Economics. I am looking for full-time work in the Washington DC metro area starting in August after I complete my degree and return to the United States. I have 3 years of full-time experience as a data analyst and statistician with R and SAS programming at the US Census Bureau and in the private sector. After gaining professional experience, I pursued graduate education to add a more modern portfolio of technical tools to my background in traditional statistics. Notable skills that I have developed during this last year include Python programming, data science through the Linux shell, working with large datasets using Spark, Hadoop, and Google Cloud Platform, and deep learning methods using the TensorFlow API. I am now looking for challenging technical work that will allow me to contribute to a team and continue to develop my skills.

EDUCATION

The London School of Economics and Political Science M.Sc. Statistics

London, United Kingdom Sep 2022 – Aug 2023

Provo, Utah, United States

- Completed elective modules emphasizing modern machine learning and deep learning methods to complement background in traditional statistics
- Modules: Statistical Inference, Generalized Linear Modeling, Bayesian Machine Learning, Distributed Computing, Deep Learning
- Sample project work: Comparing Deep Learning Approaches to Image Segmentation for Monitoring Deforestation, A Bayesian Approach to Valuing Walkable Neighborhoods in Washington DC, A Deep Learning Image Segmentation Resource for Monitoring the Great Salt Lake
- Dissertation: Estimating the causal effect of Germany's 2021 nuclear power plant closures on electricity generation using Gaussian process regression

Brigham Young University

B.S. Statistics

Jan 2016 – Dec 2019

· Minors: Mathematics, Political Science

EXPERIENCE

DevTech Systems, Inc.

Statistician

Arlington, Virginia, United States Feb 2022 – Aug 2022

- Used R and sdcMicro to apply statistical disclosure limitation methods to agency data assets to satisfy k-anonymity and reduce risk
- Performed ad-hoc analytics and visualizations using R in support of policy decisions
- Staffed on DevTech's <u>Analytics, Data, Visualization, and Information Services (ADVISE) project</u> as member of the Privacy and Risk Analysis team within <u>USAID Data Services</u> in USAID's Bureau of Management, Office of the Chief Information Officer

United States Census Bureau

Mathematical Statistician

Suitland, Maryland, United States Sep 2020 – Feb 2022

- Wrote and edited programs in SAS using SQL for production work on the <u>Survey of Income and Program Participation</u>; responsibilities included sampling, weighting, and variance estimation
- Produced estimates and updated text for the <u>Source and Accuracy statement</u> for the calendar year 2020 data release
- Reviewed Census publications which reference SIPP data for adherence to quality standards

Y2 Analytics

Data Analyst

Salt Lake City, Utah, United States Jan 2020 – Aug 2020

- Contributed to elections modeling effort by modeling education and turnout using original hierarchical Bayesian models using R
- Conducted survey research projects for <u>corporate and municipal government clients</u> from start to finish: programmed questionnaires in Qualtrics, cleaned survey data using R and y2clerk, produced graphics using ggplot2, analyzed relationships using conjoint analysis and other statistical modeling tools, and wrote text for final deliverables

Data Analyst Intern

Washington, District of Columbia, United States May 2019 – Aug 2019

Wrote new functions and corresponding unit tests for in-house R package which are still used years later by 10+ analysts

SKILLS

Key: 1 Used professionally, 2 Used in school or privately, 3 Both 1 & 2

- Programming
 - Languages: R (7 years)³, Python (1 year)², SQL (2 years)³,
 SAS (2 years)³, Bash Unix Shell (2 years)²
 - Version Control: Git³, GitHub³
 - o Testing: testthat3
- Statistical Analysis and Machine Learning
 - Theory³: Probability and inference, hypothesis testing, causal inference, linear and non-linear modeling
 - Application³: Regression, classification, clustering, Bayesian methods
- Survey Research
 - Methodology¹: sampling, weighting, & variance estimation

- o Questionnaires1: Qualtrics
- Artificial Intelligence
 - Deep Learning²
 - Frameworks: TensorFlow²
 - <u>Example</u> work (U-Net for image segmentation)
- Data Infrastructure
 - o Big Data²: Spark², Hadoop²
 - Cloud Computing²: Google Cloud Platform²
 - o Cleaning: pandas², numpy², dplyr³, tidyr³
 - Visualization: R Shiny², Tableau², ggplot2³